Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 7 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory07
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Schuyler, Philip. Albany
    Introducing his son-in-law, John Carter, and Col. [Jeremiah] Wadsworth, of Hartford, who were joint agents in supplying the French troops; they go to France to solicit payment of the bills which have been drawn in their favor; begs Franklin's influence on their behalf. Congratulating him on the approaching peace and on his exertions to that end.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 1; A.L. 2p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse, duchesse La douairière de
    Writes on behalf of two French Americans who desire to pay their respects to Franklin and dine with him on Friday or Saturday; one is her "grand garçon" and the other is the Comte de Feoren; if Franklin consents, she wishes to accompany them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 1; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Barclay, Thomas Mr. and Mrs. Auteuil
    Accepting invitation for dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Delongueville, -----. Nancy
    His intention to go to America and raise potatoes; uses of this vegetable in feeding cattle; begs for information respecting its cultivation in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Limozin, Andrew. Havre-de-Grace
    Arrival of the "General Washington," Capt. [Joshua] Barney, from Philadelphia; consigned to his care as Agent for the United States at Havre; sends several letters to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Dubosque, Fabre. Paris
    Was presented to him three years before by Commodore Paul Jones; their discussion concerning the qualities of a metal for sheathing ships; this new sheathing now carried to perfection; begs Franklin, when next he comes to Paris, to examine it at the house and talk the matter over.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 2; L.S. 3p.; Titius, Charles-Henri. Dresden
    Desiring Franklin to procure employment in America for one of his friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Stockar zur Sonnenbourg, -----. Schaffhausen
    Recommending a young relative who desires to enter the army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Titius, Charles-Henri. Dresden
    Introducing M. [Ph.] Thieriot who desires some letters of recommendation for America. Wishes to know if the sale of medicines of unkown composition will be allowed in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 4; Verse. 8p.; -------, --------
    Song composed for the anniversary celebration of American Independence and Peace held at Benjamin Franklin's house at Passy [with corrections and additions by Abbé Morellet].
  - to Benjamin Franklin and John Jay., 1783 July 5; L.S. 2p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    The King is unable to grant their request for a sum of 1,900,000 livres as extraordinary relief, as he has not enough funds to pay the enormous expenses of the last war and is obliged to have recourse to loans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Chalut and Arnous, Abbés
    Franklin made an associate of the Académic [des Sciences, Belle-Lettres et des Arts] of Lyons. Their intention of calling on him very soon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Macklot, Michel. Carlsruhe
    Wishes to establish a library and printing-house at Philadelphia for one of his sons. Gives a list of German books which he wishes to send to Philadelphia. Asking permission to send him a copy of a military work by Baron O'Cahill which he thinks will be useful to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Guillaume, Veuve. Fay-les-Veneurs
    Her frequent letters have never reached her son; begs Franklin, when he arrives in New York, to send the enclosed letter to her son, Paul Guillaume, and recommend him to the French Consul there in order that he may obtain a passage home; account of her son's services as a soldier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Tourton, -----. Paris
    Borges a merchant of Hamburg, freighted a vessel bound for Philadelphia with all his possessions, leaving nothing for his creditors; sends two letters from the Magistrates at Hamburg which he begs Franklin to forward; hopes by their means to recover what the thief carried off.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 7; L.S. 1p.; Bost Horion and Co. Paris
    Enclosing a letter of exchange drawn on Franklin which they desire him to accept and return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Webb, Benjamin. Geneva
    Congratulating him on the great events which have taken place; hopes his native country will learn the wisdom to be good. Compliments Franklin on his grandson [Benjamin Franklin Bache]; hopes his health will improve.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Ransier, Jacques Lambert. Augsburg
    Plans to go to the United States and establish a manufactory of arms; other associates who desire to go with him and establish different manufactories; begs for advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Falconer, Nathaniel. London
    Enclosing a gazette whose contents surprised him; has sent two of them to [Thomas] Mifflin in Congress; talked about it to some of the merchants; told their ships would be prevented by Congress from loading in the United States for the West Indies. Arrival of Mr. [William] Bingham and his lady.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Rosencrone, Baron -----. Copenhagen.
    Communicated his letter to the King and the draft of the proposed treaty of friendship and commerce. Sends a counter-draft drawn up by himself but not differing materially from Franklin's. Thinks it contains perfect reciprocity. Will do all in his power to accelerate the conclusion of the treaty.
    Printed in Diplom. Corres. of Am. Rev., Wharton, VI, 519.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Alexander, William. St Germain
    Requests a reply to the invitation to dine at Mme. [la Comtesse] de la Marcke's.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Lloyd, Thomas. Rouen
    Bogs that the enclosed may be forwarded. Messages from Mr. and Mrs. [Michael] Hillegas and the young ladies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 9; 1783 July 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Roi, François. Paris
    Begs for the promised reply to his father's letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.] July 10; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Blagden, Dr. Charles
    Sending him two papers printed in the Philosophical Transactions; on his return to London promises to procure all the volumes due him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Account of his business difficulties; if M. [Ferdinand] Grand cannot assist him, will let all his creditors fare alike; hopes he will not suffer in Franklin's esteem.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Price, James. Paris
    Asks permission to sell 180 hogsheads of Jamaica prize sugars, on payment of the same duties levied on French sugars.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Crocco, Giacomo Francisco. Cadiz
    The Emperor of Morocco has appointed him to be the bearer of this letter to the United States, with whom he is willing to sign a treaty of peace and commerce; gave orders to the Captains of the men-of-war not to molest American vessels. He is to accompany to the Court of Morocco, the Ambassador that is to be appointed to conclude peace. Asks him to send the travelling expenses to him as such charges are to be paid by the country desiring the Emperor's friendship.
    Printed in Diplom. Corres. of Am. Rev., Wharton, VI, 549.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Nolin, abbé -----. Paris
    Informed by M. [François Barbé] de Marbois, Secretary of the French Embassy in America, that Chevalier de la Luzerne desires an assortment of potherb seeds. Hears that the "Washington" is about to sail and that it is at Franklin's disposition; begs that the seeds may be forwarded by that vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 15; A.L. in 3d P. 4p.; Briedenstein, John Philip. "Giessac Cattorum."
    Begs to know if there is any chance of his gaining an honest livelihood in America; his position as Professor of Economics and Mathematics; his interest in theology.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Butler, John. Amsterdam
    He and two other American sailors have been prisoners in England and received their discharge some time ago; their fruitless efforts to procure a passage home at London, Dunkirk, and finally at Amsterdam; considers this hard treatment for men who risked their lives in defence of their country; depend on Franklin to extricate them from their forlorn position.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 15; L.S. 1p.; Darcel, Nicolas. Paris
    Begs him to accept and return the four enclosed bills as soon as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Alexander, William. Paris
    In case [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.] should not provide for bills drawn by Mr. [Richard] Bache, thinks Dr. Franklin would desire to do it himself, in order to save Mr. Bache the dishonor and loss of their return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Breuze, ----- de. Villentrode in Champagne
    Report that Franklin desires to establish glass-works in America; offers to furnish the kind of clay needed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Wheelock, John. London
    Wrote to him from The Hague concerning the furtherance of his plans; again begs to know whether anything can be done in France towards the accomplishment of his object.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 17; L.S. 3p.; The Farmers-General. Paris
    Remind Franklin that there is still due to them by the United States, a balance of over 846,000 livers on the advance of 1,000,000 made by them for shipments of tobacco not completed. Refrained from pressing their claim during the war and do not ask any interest on the money, but request a prompt settlement either in cash or in tobacco.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Falconer, Nathaniel. London
    Visit paid him by Mr. Silas Deane; understands he wrote part of the pamphlet sent to Franklin; cannot esteem him as before, now that he goes with [Benedict] Arnold and Lord Sheffield. Dr. [Edward] Bancroft is applying to go to Philadelphia; distrusts his motives. Messages from Mr. [John] Sargent. Begs for news of public matters in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Diot, John. Morlaix
    Various ways in which he has been of use to subjects of the United States; asks for the position of Vice-Consul at Morlaix; his zeal in the service of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Polignac, Charles, comte de. Paris
    Mme. de Frère, being obliged to take a short journey, desires him to return the enclosed bill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783, July 19; A.L.S. 4p.; Capion, -----. Lyons
    A glowing tribute to Franklin. His occupation that of a doctor as well as priest. Describes the plan of a picture which he wishes to present to Congress; this will represent the heroes of the American war, the traitor Arnold, the victim André, the brutality of the English, the mediation of France, and Heaven's approval of the struggle for liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Austin, Jonathan Loring. Boston
    Introducing his brother, Mr. Benjamin Austin, Jr. and Mr. Oliver Brewster, two young gentlemen who are making a tour of Europe. Congratulating Franklin on the peace and on his own distinguished part in that glorious event.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Introducing Mr. Benjamin Austin, Jr., a brother of Mr. [Jonathan Loring] Austin who carried the news of Burgoyne's surrender; recommends him most warmly to his notice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Introducing Mr. [Oliver] Brewster who goes to England with Mr. [Benjamin] Austin and thence to France on mercantile affairs; the particulars regard he has conceived for this young man justifies this recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 19; A.L.S. 4p.; Joy, Henry Jr. Belfast
    Writes in the name of the Committee of Correspondence appointed by the delegates of forty-five Volunteer Corps; their determination to procure a more equal representation in Parliament; depraved state of their present representation; desires Franklin's opinion and advice as to the best means of countcracting the corrupt borough influence; puts the whole matter into eight queries to which they beg answers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 19; L. in 3d P. 1p.; The Ambassador of Portugal. Paris
    Informing Franklin that the meeting to be held in his house will be held in the house of the Spanish Ambassador.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779?] July 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Boulainvilliers, Mme de
    Requests an interview with Franklin about an unfortunate man in whom she is interested.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 19; A.L.S. 4p.; Hoppe, Jacob Augustus. Bochnia
    Is one of a numerous family; would like to sail for the United States with a recommendation from Franklin and the assurance of a salaried position; is even willing to till the fields; if possible, would like to stay for a time in Paris and pursue his study of English at the Sorbonne; in that case would be glad to share the food of Franklin's servants.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Schönfeld, -----, baron de.
    Desiring to call on Franklin in company with M. [Ph.] Thieriot of Leipsic, who goes to Philadelphia as a commercial agent of Saxony.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    The Corntesse de Deux-Ponts hopes to visit Franklin after her return from Versailles; in the meantime, she begs for a medal in place of the one she gave M. de Vauban, and also the return of Les Nouvelles Littéraires which she sent Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Watson, Elkanah Jr
    Introducing Griffin Green[e], lately arrived from America, a near relative of Gen. [Nathanael] Green[e].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 222; A.L.S. 2p.; Small, Alexander. London
    Desires his opinion on the chief cause of the suffering experienced by the garrison of St. Philips; believes it was their omitting to preserve a free current of air through their subterranean lodgements. Introducing Partick Wikil, Esq., who goes as Consul to Alicante; hopes of seeing Franklin in London; glad that the remembrance of a most agreeable fair one is still with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 22; L.in 3d P. 1p.; Melville, Robert. Paris
    Announcing his intended departure for London early in the following week; offers to take charge of the letter to Mr. [John] Calder, as well as any Mr. [John] Adams or Mr. and Mrs. [John] Jay care to send.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Montcarel, Jean-Jacques Le Goüeslier de. Versailles
    Concerning a packet which was forgotten when the despatches were sent to be forwarded to M. de la Luzerne; if not too late, begs it may be sent, and the oversight not mentioned to M. [Joseph Matthias Gérard de Rayneval.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Miromesnil, Armand-Thomas Hué de. Paris
    Acknowledging the receipt of the Constitutions of the United States; expressing his appreciation of such a mark of attention.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 24; L. in 3d P. 2p.; Pio, Luigi de
    Acknowledging the copies of the "Constitutions," one for his King, one for himself and one for M. Filangieri; Sensible of the honor Franklin has done him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 24; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Argental, Charles-Augustin Ferriol, comte d'. Paris
    Acknowledging with extreme satisfaction the copy of the Constitutions of the United States which Franklin has sent him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 24; A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; Boufflers-Rouvrel, Marie-Charlotte-Hippolyte de Campet de Sanjon, comtesse de. Auteuil
    Acknowledging Franklin's precious gift, with every expression of gratitude.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Acknowledging his gift with the liveliest expressions of gratitude; reminding him of his promise to visit her in the autumn.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 25; L in 3d P. 1p.; The Ambassador of Holland. Paris
    Thanking him for the "Constitutions of the Thirteen United States of America."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 25; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Acknowledging the copy of the "Constitutions" of the United States sent him by Franklin; the copies destined for the King, Queen and Royal Family will be faithfully delivered.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Tonon, -----. Paris
    The most unfortunate of patriots is obliged to apply to the most illustrious; although in disgrace, still wishes to be useful; his principal bent is towards agriculture; has written a trcatise on this science; desires to place his talents at the service of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 July 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Harvey, Reuben. Cork
    Two vessels lately sailed for Philadelphia with upwards of two hundred passengers. Account of an American vessel, the "Nancy," being detained in the harbor of Castleton nearly ten weeks; wrote Mr. [Henry] Laurens of this; advises an application for redress to the British Court; other vessels had all their loose tobacco seized by Revenue Officers; necessity of America having a Consul at Cork; state of the laws in Ireland as regards the sale of tobacco.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 July 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Granier de Pollier, -----. Paris
    Recommending a gentleman of quality, formerly a French officer, who desires to settle with his wife in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 July 26; L.S. 1p.; Ormesson, Henri-François de Paul Le Feurè d'. Versailles
    Thanking him for the copy of the Constitutions of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 July 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Walterstorff, M de
    Sends Franklin a copy of the last ordinance concerning the trade of the Islands of St. Thomas and St. Johns [2p.], also a list of the principal merchants in the Danish West Indies (2p.). The Island of St. Croix and their trade with America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 July 6; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Rochambeau, Jean-Baptiste-Donatien de Vimeur, comte de. Paris
    Begs to have the enclosed letter forwarded to the Chevalier de la Luzerne.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 July 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging a number of introductory letters which has been productive of pleasure of profit. The bearer is Mr. [John] Carter by whom he sends a bundle of newspapers; Mrs. Carter is the daughter of Gen. [Philip] Schuyler, a lady too well known to Franklin to need a recommendation. Has received the Loan Office Certificate for another year's interest on the money lent the public by Franklin. Glad to know when they may expect him home.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Lamoligniere, ----- Duboys de. Port-au-Prince
    Recounts the legend concerning the purchase of the Sibylline books; the printed discourse which he sends Franklin of far more value than vain oracles; the system of Legislations on which he has worked for seven years will put the seal on the liberties of America.
    (In French. In Duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 28; L. in 3d P. 2p.; The Apostolic Nuncio
    The Congregation for the Propagation of the Faith at Rome has deemed it advisable to appoint a Bishop in some city of the United States as Apostolic Vicar with spiritual jurisdiction over all the Catholics in that country and invested with power to ordain priests. requests Franklin to transmit his note on the subject to Congress.
    Printed in Diploma. Corres. of Am. Rev., Wharton, VI, 614.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Strange, Isabella. London
    Begs him to send the enclosed letter to her friend Mr. [James] Hunter [of Richmond, Va.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 29; L.S. 1p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre
    Sends the desired permission to enable Franklin to remove a packet of books from the custom-house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 29; A.L.S. 5p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Consultation with his creditors; their desire that his letter of surséance be renewed for a year; desires Franklin to make the application for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 30; A.L.S 2p.; Alexander, Williams. Paris
    Concerning the affairs of [Jonathan] W[illiams] and the terms of payment offered, to which most of his people have agreed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 30; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Cambray-Digny, Louis-Antoine-Jean-Baptiste, chevalier de. Paris
    About to leave for the country; sends some letters for America, and begs that the replies may be forwarded to the address given.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 30; A.L.S. 4p.; L. 2p.; de Qureille, Chevalier Charles. Giessen
    Suggests the importance of establishing commercial relations between America and the principal German towns on the Rhine and Main; recommends a friend as an Agent in these towns. Enumeration of products.
    The same
    (Translation in French)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Truton de Sibery, François. Nantes
    Begging him to honor with his attention the enclosed memoir.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Churchill, C. Bennet St. West
    Begging Franklin to honor his last with some kind of an answer; if his request is not granted, entreats some kind of assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 July 31; A.L.S. 5p.; Herman Heyman's Sons. Bremen
    Their project to establish glass-works in America; privileges which they would ask of Congress; begs Franklin's advice on this subject; enclosing a detailed plan [4p.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 1; A. Poem. 7p.; Coquillot, -----, Prior of Epinay. Louviers
    Ode to Liberty composed in honor of Benjamin Franklin on receiving from him the medal struck by the Congress of the United States in 1782.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 1; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Marat, Jean Paul. Paris
    Requesting an audience with Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Joshua. London
    Forwards a letter from the General Post Office and has paid the deficient postage. Probable that many letters may come for him with the inland postage unpaid. Inquires if he shall take them up and forward them. Will be happy to be useful to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Lettsom, John Coakley. London
    Introducing Henry Smeathman, a protégé of Dr. Fothergill, who visited the Coast of Africa and wishes to suggest new ways of extending trade in that continent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Braumüller, John Gottfried. Berlin
    Desires recommendations to American mercantile firms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Deslande, Loyer. Versailles
    The business which her husband transacted in America in 1777 is the reason for her requesting an immediate audience with Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 2; A.L.S. 4p.; Sandherr, -----. Versailles
    Desires to establish a market in America for the sale of his wines.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 3; L.S. 2p.; Monet, -----, comte de
    Acknowledging enthusiastically the copies of the Constitutions, one for the King of Poland and one for himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 3; L. in 3d P. 1p.; The Ambassador of the States-General. Paris
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 August 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Steinsky, François. Prague